Now we can get started creating some
それではゲームのスクリプト作成を
scripts for the game. The first one we're
始めます。最初に作ってみるのは
going to make will be to control the alarm light.
アラームライトを制御するもので
When the player triggers the alarm we want
プレイヤーがアラームのトリガーを引いた時に呼ばれます。
the light to pulse. So create a new C# script
ライトの光り方は脈打つように制御させたいため、
called AlarmLight on the alarm
新規 C# スクリプト AlarmLight を
light game object by selecting it,
アタッチする AlarmLight ゲームオブジェクトを選択して
and then clicking Add Component - New Script.
Add Component - New Script とクリックします。
Name the script AlarmLight.
Alarm Script と名前をつけます。
Remember to match the capitalisation
大文字小文字を
exactly as we're doing it.
間違えないようにします。
Click Create and Add
Create をクリックして追加し、
and then double click on the icon to
アイコンをダブルクリックして編集できるようにします。
launch it for editing. We will start this
はじめに Unity デフォルトで挿入される
script by removing the defaults that Unity
コード部分を削除して
puts in so that we can start afresh.
ゼロベースから始めます。
Remove the Start and Update function
Start() および Update() 関数について
and the comments that are there with it.
付随するコメント文とともに削除します
Now we have an empty class we can add
これで空のクラスが出来ました。
some class variables.
次にクラス変数を追加していきます。
Firstly we'll need to make the public one.
最初は public から作成します。
We're going to make a series of floats
float を複数追加して、
as the parameters that control the different
制御用のパラメータとして
intensities of the light and how
様々なライト強度を制御する変数、
fast we fade between them.
ライト強度の間をフェードするスピードの変数を追加します。
Firstly, the fade speed.
ではフェードするスピードから始めます。
We'll set a default of 2, but this can be
デフォルトで 2.0 の値にしますが、インスペクタで後ほど
tweaked later in the inspector if we like.
自由に調整できます。
Next we'll need a couple more floats
次にライトが
to represent the high and low intensities
明るい/暗いときの強度をあらわす float
we want to light to fade between.
を追加して、それらの値の間をフェードさせます。
2 and 0.5 should be appropriate defaults,
2.0 および 0.5 にすれば適切な値ですが
but again we can tweak them later in the
調整したければ後からインスペクタ上で
inspector if we want.
次に Lerp 関数を使用して
we will be using the Lerp function
これらの値の間を
to change between these two values.
変化するようにします。
The way that we are using this means that
今回は終点に近づくにつれ
the change in value slows down as it
スローダウンする
reaches it's target.
ようにします。
As such we will want to change the fade
そのためには
to the opposite intensity before we reach
フェードのスピードを逆側の終点のターゲット強度に到達するまでに
the target intensity.
変化させます。
We will need to have a margin within which
このために、ターゲットを逆側の終点に
we are able to change the target
設定する境界値も
to it's opposite.
追加していきます。
The last public variable we will need is
最後に必要となる public 変数は
a boolean that says whether or not
boolean であり
the alarm is on. This needs to be public,
アラームがオンかどうか示します。
not for tweaking in the inspector but
これを public とする意味はインスペクタ上で編集する目的ではなく、
because we want to effect it from another script,
別スクリプト参照するためであり、
which decides whether the alarm needs
アラームがオンであるべきかを判断させることが
to be on or not.
できます。
We still need another class variable, although
さらに必要なクラス変数は、
we can make this one private.
private としても問題ありません。
This will be to store the intensity we are
ライトを変化させるときのターゲットとなる
trying to fade the light towards.
ライト強度を格納します。
Now that we have our class variables
これでクラス変数の追加は完了し、
we can setup any behaviours we want at
シーンの最初で必要な処理を
the start of the scene. We do this
行うようにします。
in the Awake function. Add this now.
その処理は Awake 関数で行います。ここで追加して下さい。
Since at the start of the scene the alarm
シーンの最初ではアラームは
will be off. We want the lights intensity
オフであるためライト強度が
to be 0.
ゼロになるようにします。
We also want the first intensity the light
さらにアラームが
transitions to when the alarm is activated
有効化された直後は
to be high intensity.
ライト強度が最大値に遷移するようにします。
Now we have our Update function where we
次は Update 関数ですが
perform most of the script's operations.
スクリプト処理のほとんどがここでなされ、
Add this now.
ここで追加して下さい。
The first thing we want to do in each update
各々の Update ごとにやりたいことは
is to check whether the AlarmOn variable
AlarmOn 変数が
has been set to True.
true であるかチェックすることです。
If it has then we want to lerp the light's
true であればライト強度で Lerp を用いて、現在のライト強度と
intensity between it's current setting
ターゲット強度の間を
and the target intensity. We want to include
行き来するようにします。
the fade speed in the last parameter
フェードするスピードを最後の引数で含めるようにして
so that we can tweak how fast this lerp happens.
どれぐらいの速度とするか調整できるようにします。
Next, given that the light's intensity
次にライト強度が
has been updated, we want to check
更新されているものとして、
if it's near enough to the target intensity
ライト強度がターゲット強度に近い値となり
for us to switch the target to it's opposite.
今度はターゲットを逆の端に変更して良いか判定を行います。
For example if it's heading towards
例えば、もしライト強度が最も明るくなるようになっていたとして
the high intensity - if we are within the margin -
ある範囲まで近づくと
then we will head towards the low intensity.
今度は最も暗くなるところに近づくようにターゲットを変更します。
To do this we are going to make a new function
これを実現するには Update 関数の中で
which we will call in the update.
新しい関数をコールするようにします。
Move below the closing of the update function
それでは Update 関数の終わりの } の直後まで移動して
and add a new function called
"Check Target Intensity" という新しい関数を
CheckTargetIntensity.
追加します。
So in this function we need to know if
この関数では
the difference between the target intensity
ターゲット強度と、
and the light's current intensity
現在のライト強度の間の差分を調べる必要があり、
is less than the change margin.
その差分が一定値を下回ったかどうかを見ます。
To get the difference between the target intensity
ターゲット強度と、
and the light's intensity
現在のライト強度の間の差分を調べるには
we will use a function called Abs
Mathf クラスの
in the Mathf class.
Abs() 関数を使用します。
It simply returns the absolute value,
この関数は
that is, the positive version of whatever is
引数として渡した数字を絶対値、すなわち
passed as a parameter.
正の値に変換して戻します。
If this is the case then we need to set
この場合は
the target intensity to the opposite
ターゲットのライト強度を
of what it was.
反対の端の値に変更する必要があります。
So we check if the target is high.
ターゲット強度が最大の明るさかどうかをチェックして
And if it is, then we set the target to low.
もしそうであれば最小の明るさをセットして
Otherwise we set the target to high.
反対にそうでなければ最大の明るさをセットします。
With the CheckTargetIntensity function finished
CheckTargetIntensity 関数が完了したら
we can put a call to it if the alarm
コールが行われるように
is on in our Update function.
Update 関数の中に Alarm を含めるようにします。
Note that in this approach the light's
この方法によってライト強度の
intensity will fade in and out smoothly
フェードイン、フェードアウトはスムーズに行われ、
as the lerp's value will slow as it
Lerp された値はターゲットに近づくにつれて
reaches it's target.
遅くなることに留意して下さい。
To simplify this we could have implemented
これを単純化するには別の便利な関数を実装することも出来ます。
another useful function called Mathf.PingPong.
それはMathf.Pingpongと呼ばれます。
This is designed to simply return values
この関数が行うことは
that loop between 0 and a given value.
ゼロと与えられた変数との間の値を戻すものですが、
But this would not look smooth as it's
この場合は遷移のスピードが一定値であるため
transitions have a constant speed.
スムーズな動きには見えなくなります。
That concludes what needs to happen if the alarm
以上でアラームがオンの場合の処理は完了です。
is on. But when the alarm is off
しかし、アラームがオフの場合は
we need to turn the intensity back down to 0.
ライト強度をゼロに戻す必要があります。
Add an Else to the If statement
Update 関数にある if 文に
in the Update function.
else を追加します。
And here we will put a similar line to our
ここでライト強度に対して、同様の Lerpを使用して
light intensity lerp, but set the value to 0.
今回は値にゼロをセットします。
That's all we need to do with this script,
以上でスクリプトに対する変更は完了であるため、
so save the script and return to the editor.
保存したうえでエディタに戻ります。
You'll notice that all of our public variables
すぐに気付くことですが public 変数はスクリプト
will appear on the script component
がアタッチされているインスペクタク上で
in the inspector.
表示されます。
Now we have something else we need
次にアラームに対して行うべき変更が
to do for the alarm.
残っています。
We need it to actually make an alarm sound
アラーム音の再生を実装する必要があります。
You may have noticed that there are some
お気づきかもしれませんが、レベルのあちこちに
megaphone towers around the level.
スピーカーが配置されてます。
Each of these is going to play an
各々のスピーカーはアラームのサウンドエフェクト再生を行います。
alarm sound effect. For this we need to setup
これを行うためにはいくつかセットアップが必要な内容があります。
a few things. Start by expanding
早速作業に入るために
env_stealth_static. Then expand props
まずはenv_stealth_staticを展開して次にpropsを展開します。
and locate all of the prop_megaphone game objects.
prop_megaphoneゲームオブジェクトに対してまとめて
Highlight them all with shift-selection
Shift を押しながら選択すること複数選択をすれば
and now that they're highlighted we can
変更を全てに同時反映することが
effect them all simultaneously.
出来るようになります。
We will start by tagging them all
それでは全て同じタグをつけますが、
with the tag Siren.
Siren というタグをつけましょう。
We also want to add an audio source component
またそれぞれに対してオーディオソースを追加することで
to each of them so that they can play audio clips.
オーディオクリップの再生が出来るようにします。
Click on the Add Component button in the inspector
インスペクタ上のAdd Componentボタンをクリックして
and go to Audio - Audio Source.
Audio - Audio Source を開きます。
Lastly we want to make sure that the audio
最後にオーディオ ソースのセットアップが正しいかを
source is setup correctly.
確認することにします。
In the Audio folder in the project panel
プロジェクトパネルの Audio フォルダをみてみると、オーディオクリップのなかで
you will see a clip called AlarmTriggered.
Alarm Triggeredと書かれたものが見つかります。
Drag and drop this to the audio clip property.
これをAudipo Clipプロパティ上にドラッグ＆ドロップします。
We don't want them to play this sound on awake,
今回はゲーム開始時に再生されるための
meaning 'when the game begins', but we
Play On Awake は無効にして、
do want them to loop when they are playing it.
再生時の Loop は有効とします。
Now is a good time to adjust the range of the towers.
次に各々のタワーの音の範囲を調整するため
Do so by opening the 3D sound settings
3D Sound Settings を
on the audio source component.
Audio Source コンポーネント上でみつけて
And set the Min Distance value to a value of 5.
Min Distanceの値を 5 にセットします。
You should see in the scene view that there
シーンビューにおいて
are blue spherical outlines showing
青い球状の線が表示されたものが
you the reach of these towers.
各タワーの音の範囲に相当します
If you want them to be louder in the game you
もしゲームでより大きな音にしたい場合は
can adjust this value later.
後ほど調整することも出来ます。
That's all we need to do for the setup of the alarm.
以上でアラームのセットアップの必要な作業は完了です。
Remember to save your scene now by going to
ここで忘れずに保存するため
File - Save Scene and move on the next
FileメニューからSave Sceneを選びます。
assignment where we will be creating a library
次のビデオではゲームで使用するタグの一覧を作成して
of tags for use within our game controller.
Game Controller 中で使用することにします。 (翻訳:gamesonytablet)